The Hudson River Ships and Commerce Collection
Marist College Archives and Special Collections
The Hudson River Ships and Commerce Collection
1800 - 1876
NPkMC-223-082
0.5 Linear Feet
Marist College Archives and Special Collections
Collection Overview
This collection includes documents from the 19th century pertaining to commerce of ships on the Hudson River including a list of ships, bills of sale of ships and bills and receipts for money lending and goods. Also included are handwritten letters and poems and pages from “The Life and Adventures of Captain Thomas Adams” apparently written by Captain Thomas Adams. There are also a number of Graphic materials depicting the various vessels.
The Hudson River Ships and Commerce Collection were given to the Marist College Library by the Hudson River Sloop Clearwater, Inc.
Historical Note
There is a rich history of nautical travel along the Hudson River by the means of steamboats, sloops, and barges. This collection chronicles some of the many vessels that made their way up and down the Hudson River during the 1800s and the business transactions related to them. The invention of the steamboat in 1807 made such travel fast and affordable and by 1850 approximately 150 were making regular voyages on the river (For more information: http://www.hudsonriver.com/hudson-river-history). Ships such as the Albany ran from New York City to Poughkeepsie, a distance of 75 miles, in little over three hours and had the capacity to carry as many as 4,500 passengers. The Peoples-Citizens lines, organized in the 1870s included floating palaces like the Adirondack and CW Morse which included as many as 400 state rooms as well as parlors and private baths. The collection also includes the many sloops of the Hudson River. A sloop is a sail boat with a fore-and-aft rig, one mast and a single jib. The Hudson River Sloop Clearwater is an example of a modern replica. Appreciation of the beauty of the Hudson River inspired poems and songs that are included in this collection as well as the writings and letters pertaining to traveling the river.
There are no restrictions on this collection
Arrangement of the Collection
These records are organized into three series: 1) Ship documents, 2) Bills and Receipts, and 3) Letters, Journals, Poems and Songs
Materials are arranged chronologically or by subject
- 1. Ship Documents, 1982 - 1835; 1; Box: 1 Folder: 1 Number of Items: 4
  - Bill of Sale of the Schooner “Victory of Hempsted” to Gilbert D. Craft, Willet Craft, and Thomas Comb by Caleb Mott., February 11, 1829; 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bill of Sale of the “Marshall of Coxsackie” to William Sherwood by Byron Cook., August 26, 1834; 2 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bill of Sale of a sloop to William Sherwood by Byron Cook., March 1, 1835; 3 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Lists of Hudson River Steamboats, Sloops, Barges, Brick and Hay Barges, Ice Barges, Duck Scows, Lighters, Towing Lines and Steam Tugs (pages 35-72)., undated; 4 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- 2. Bills and Receipts, 1800 - 1876; 2; Box: 1 Folder: 2 Number of Items: 28
  - Receipt of funds from Stewart& Townsend by John B. Limicane for wheat., December 1800; 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Receipt of funds from Stewart& Townsend by Benjamin Howland for freight., December 4, 1800; 2 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Receipt of funds from Stewart& Townsend by Alexander Reilly for freight., December 4, 1800; 3 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Receipt from Stewart& Townsend by John Bifsel for passage to Albany., December 10, 1800; 4 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bill to Captain Stewart from Thomas Gould., March 21, 1801; 5 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Receipt of funds from Captain Olmsted by George Ramsay for wheat., July 24, 1801; 6 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Receipt of funds from Captain Thomas Carpinter by John Pintard for iron and steel freight., July 31, 1801; 7 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bill and receipt of funds from Captain Monted by V.J. Rufsell., August 1801; 8 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Receipt of funds from Stewart& Townsend by Francis March for leterage of the Sloop “Diana”., September 2, 1801; 9 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Receipt of funds from Isaiah Townsend by John Vernon., April 7, 1803; 10 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bill and receipt of funds from Captain Stewart by Thomas and William Mott., April 4, 1807; 11 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Measuring Bill to Robert Mott from Andrew Hegeman for wheat., April 14, 1808; 12 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Receipt of funds from Captain Craft of the Schooner “Mary Elmy” by W. Gillman for sundries and a top sail., December 3, 1840; 13 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Receipt of funds from Captain Craft of the Schooner “Mary Elmy” by William Heillman., July 17, 1841; 14 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Note from the Collector’s Office to Thomas Adams concerning the expired license of the Scow “Dispatch”., December 3, 1842; 15 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bill and receipt of funds from the Sloop “Marshall” by Waldron Shear., July 17, 1846; 16 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bill and receipt of funds from Captain Adams by Ira Hutchinson for rope and tar., October 5, 1847; 17 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bill and receipt of funds from Mr. Adams by C.& J.L. Van Deusen., May 10, 1858; 18 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bill and receipt of funds from Gilbert Craft by Richard Browen for lumber., Febuary 12, 1865; 19 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bill and receipt from Thomas Adams for freight., February 16, 1869; 20 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bill to Boat “Meagor” for Towing., September 23, 1869; 21 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bill and receipt of funds from Mr. Adams by Ward, Leonard & Co., May 12, 1870; 22 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bill to the Canal Boat “Major” from William Bradley for dockage., September 13, 1871; 23 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bill and receipt of funds from Thomas Ackerman by Everson & Bullen for pitch., May 2, 1872; 24 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bill from the Delaware and Hudson Canal Company to Charles R. Gill., June 7, 1872; 25 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Trimming bill and receipt of funds from the Sloop “Accommodation”., August 22, 1876; 26 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Trimming bill and receipt of funds from the Sloop “Accommodation”., October 9, 1876; 27 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bill for Seasonwork on the Schooner “Mary Almy”, undated; 28 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- 3. Letters, Journals, Poems and Songs, 1800 - 1846; 3; Box: 1 Folder: 3 Number of Items: 11
  - Letter to D.W. Wilson from Beekman., June 20, 1800; 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letter to Thomas Reed from his cousin Kate., September 5, 1841; 2 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letter to Cora Van Keuren from her cousin Jacob F. Hagadorn., August 8, 1846; 3 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letter to Cora from her brother Leonard A. Reily., May 18, 1847; 4 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Pages from “The Life and Adventures of Captain Thomas Adams”., undated; 5 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Pages from “The Life and Adventures of Captain Thomas Adams”., undated; 6 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Pages from “The Life and Adventures of Captain Thomas Adams”., undated; 7 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Pages from “The Life and Adventures of Captain Thomas Adams”., undated; 8 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Pages from “The Life and Adventures of Captain Thomas Adams”., undated; 9 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - “The Hudson River”, a poem composed by Sadye A. Beaver of Johustown, New York., undated; 10 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - “The New Song of Bonapart”., undated; 11 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- 4. Images, 4; Box: 1 Folder: 4 Number of Items: 7
  - Picture of the “Adirondack”, undated; 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Picture of the Steamer “Albany”, undated; 2 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Picture: The Hudson River Day Line Steamer “Albany”, undated; 3 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Picture: Steamer “C. W. Morse”, undated; 4 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Picture: New Steamer, “Rensselaer,” Citizens Line, undated; 5 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Picture of a Boat, “Russells”, undated; 6 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Page of Kodax Panatomic X Film showing pictures from ‘Picturesque America, undated; 7 (Box 1, Folder 4)